Guide to the Arthur Tress Photographs M2214
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Arthur Tress photographs
1965-1983
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Tress, Arthur
M2214
2 Linear Feet (58 prints in two boxes)
Prints by American photographer Arthur Tress.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Tress (Nov. 24, 1940- ) has had an extremely active career and is well published, with much of his work incorporating his role as both director and photographer. His photographs engage a rich visual symbolism, often presenting dream-like, childhood states. He has also documented San Francisco in the 1960s and composed and photographed fantasy toy stage settings, such as the Teapot Opera. Over his career his work has been constantly inventive, often playful, always psychologically probing. Born in Brooklyn in 1940, Tress began his photography career as a teenager, photographing the dilapidated buildings and denizens of Coney Island. Early on he developed an interest in ethnographic photography and the production of photographic narratives, which led to a commission from the New York State Council on the Arts to produce Open space in the inner city; ecology and the urban environment (1971). His book, The Dream collector (1972), with staged photographic work based on his interviews with children and employing these same children to perform their dreams is now considered a classic in the photobook literature. With Theater of the mind (1976) Tress moved to adult fantasies and begins a period of overtly erotic work. In Facing up (alternatively titled Phallic phantasy, (1980), Tress moved to overtly gay photographic work. In more recent years Tress has continued in the “directorial mode,” and worked in color with miniature stage settings, producing The Teapot opera and the Fish tank sonata. He continues to actively photograph and exhibit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Anonymous gift; 2017. Accession MSS 2017-111.
Scope and Contents
58 approximately 8" x 10" prints by photographer Arthur Tress. Most of the prints are on double weight gelatin silver paper and are dry mounted on board.
Photography, Artistic; Tress, Arthur
- Series 1. Appalachia: People and Places
  Scope and Contents
  In 1968 Tress had his first one-person exhibition "Appalachia--People and Places", which was held at the Smithsonian Institute and the Sierra Gallery in New York City.
  - AT.2007.5774 North Carolina, Elk Park. Children of Unemployed Miners Live in Squalor, Play With Dirty Doll, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series 2. Bagman
  - AT.2007.3568 Bagman, NY, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AT.2007.3575 Bagman, NY, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series 3. Dream Collector
  - AT.2013.10338 Hockey Glove Fantasy, NY, NY (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AT.2013.10343 Boy in Flood Dream, NY, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AT.2013.10349 Philip Hecksher's Dream, Bar Harbor, Maine (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - AT.2013.10373 Girl in Aquarium with Sea Mammals, San Francisco, California, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - AT.2013.10378 Boy Listening to Musician, Biloxi, Miss., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AT.2013.10384 Girl in White Dress in Interior, Cape May, NJ, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - AT.2013.10402 Flying Dream, Queens, NY, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - AT.2013.10405 Boy in Labyrinth Maze, NY, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - AT.2016.10745 P.S.3 Dream Workshop, Rabbit by Window, NY, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series 4. Elmer
  - AT.2007.3354 Elmer is a Political Prisoner, NY, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - AT.2007.3372 Elmer at End of Day, NY, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - AT.2007.3375 Elmer At Peep Show, NY, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - AT.2007.3392 Elmer Takes the Temperature, NY, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - AT.2007.3422 Elmer Uses a Caliper, NY, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - AT.2007.3502 Elmer Inside Clock, E.H., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series 5. Eskimo
  - AT.2012.9534 Eskimo Shaman, Point Hope, Alaska, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series 6. India
  - AT.2012.9520 Cow Horns, Toda Tribe, India, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Series 7. Japan
  - AT.2012.9545 Fishing Floats, Japan, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - AT.2012.9548 Hiroshima, 1965. Double Exposure Showing Before + After Effects of Bomb (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series 8. Male Nude/Gay/Facing Up
  - AT.2007.6312 Pool Attendant, Miami Beach, Florida, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - AT.2008.1907 Nude In Cemetery, Brooklyn, NY, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - AT.2008.1916 Nude with Jeans, NY, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - AT.2008.1938 Corn God, New Hope, Pa., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - AT.2008.1949 Pier Cruising, NY, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - AT.2008.1963 After the Bomb, Brooklyn, NY, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - AT.2008.2002 Leather Couple in Doorway, NY, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - AT.2008.2124 The Ledger Book, NY, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - AT.2008.2239 The Prussian Soldier + Drinking Comrade, NY, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - AT.2008.2246 2 Leather Guys in Pier Doorways, NY, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - AT.2008.2253 Follow the Rules, NY, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - AT.2008.2363 Jung's dream, NY, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - AT.2008.2608 Rooftop Duet, NY, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - AT.2008.2613 Viper Vites, NY, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - AT.2008.6198 Man and Pump, NY (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - AT.2009.6211 Man in Black Tape, NY (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - AT.2009.6221 Grooming, NY (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - AT.2009.6274 The Gardener's Fantasy, Cold Spring, NY, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - AT.2009.6292 Couple, NY, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - AT.2009.6308 Mousetrap, NY, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - AT.2009.6309 Urban Cowboy, NY, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - AT.2009.6315 Wounded Soldier, NY, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - AT.2009.6317 Wrench Fantasy, NY, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - AT.2009.6334 Pier Guy, NY, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series 9. San Francisco
  - AT.2007.6700 Man on Bench, SF, CA, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series 10. Shadow
  - AT.2007.0744 Shadow King under El, NY, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - AT.2007.0746 Shadow on Subway Stairs, NY, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - AT.2007.0776 Shadow Feeding Giant Eagle, NY, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - AT.2007.1771 Shadow: The Town, Arles, France, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series 11. Spray
  - AT.2007.0146 Oscillating Functions, NY, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series 12. Still Life
  - AT.2007.3833 Tennis Anyone? Light Box Collage, NY, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - AT.2007.3870 Virgo, Collage, NY, Astrology Page, Magazine, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - AT.2007.3871 Father of the Bride, Collage, NY, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series 13. Teapot Opera
  - AT.2007.4425 TPO, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - AT.2007.4510 TPO, I, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - AT.2007.4544 TPO, II, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 24)